Guide to the American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Records WAG.099
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Records
1930-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Postal Workers Union
Biller, Moe, 1915-2003
Burrus, William
WAG.099
15.75 Linear Feet in 7 record boxes, 4 flat oversize boxes, and 1 exhibit case.
Moe Biller served as president of the New York Metro Area Postal Union (originally the Postal Union of Manhattan-Bronx Clerks) from 1959 to 1980. As local president, Biller led the New York City union through the hard-fought national postal strike of 1970. From 1980 until his retirement in 2001, Biller was president of the American Postal Workers Union. This collection is composed of selected APWU presidential files, documentation of an oral history project carried out by retirees of the New York Metro Area Postal Union in the late 1970s, as well as a selection of printed items, including photographs and protest materials, as well as numerous physical artifacts in the form of plaques and awards.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
Moe Biller's life-long interest in the preservation of labor history inspired him to mark his retirement from the American Postal Workers Union by donating a selection of his presidential files, as well as his personal collection of memorabilia, signed photographs, posters, and books on postal union history to the Robert Wagner Labor Archives at New York University. Incoming APWU president William Burrus confirmed the donation and designated the Robert Wagner Labor Archives as the official repository for APWU records at the same time. In 2001, the union also transferred to NYU a body of records documenting the New York Metro Area Postal Union oral history project; these were apparently given to Biller during his tenure as New York Metro president.
Historical/Biographical Note
Morris "Moe" Biller was born in New York City on November 15, 1915. He attended Brooklyn College and City College and began working in the Postal Service in 1937 as a substitute clerk. Except for wartime service in the military, Biller spent the rest of his life in the Postal Service and as a postal union leader. He held almost every position within his local union (National Federation of Postal Clerks, Local 10) before the local broke away to become the Manhattan-Bronx Postal Workers, a local of the newly formed National Postal Clerks Union. Biller became president of the new local, 25,000 members strong, in 1959 and led the local through the so-called Great Postal Strike of 1970. This national strike lasted eight days and resulted in the Postal Reorganization Act of 1970, creating the U.S. Postal Service and granting its employees collective bargaining rights. In 1971 the National Postal Clerks Union joined with four other postal unions to become the American Postal Workers Union. Biller's local took on its present name, the New York Metro Area Postal Union, in 1973; the new name reflected the inclusion of the New York Bulk and Foreign Mail Center and the North Jersey Facility in the local's bargaining unit.
Biller was elected president of the American Postal Workers Union in 1980, and carried his activist style into this new arena. He was a long-time supporter of the civil rights movement and of women's efforts to advance in the labor movement. He served on the boards of numerous charitable organizations, including the March of Dimes and United Way, and sat on the boards of university labor studies programs at Cornell University and Empire State College. Biller's personal interest in labor history was exemplified in the cooperation he offered to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University, to the Tenement Museum on New York's Lower East Side, and to a number of labor history oral history and film projects. It was with his full and enthusiastic support that Dana Schechter embarked on her project to document the history of the New York Metro Area Postal Union through interviews with and by the local's retirees. On his retirement Biller returned to live in his beloved New York City; he died in New York on September 5, 2003.
Sources:
Walsh, John and Garth Mangum, Labor Struggle in the Post Office: From Selective Lobbying to Collective Bargaining (New York: M. E. Sharpe, 1992).
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the American Postal Workers Union from the perspective of its former president, Moe Biller. Biller was a long-time labor activist and also an active civil rights supporter. The American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Records contain materials documenting the health and safety hazards posed to postal workers, as well as the union's energetic attempts to improve working conditions. Also included are a range of records and printed ephemera documenting the Depression-era history of U.S. postal workers and their organizations.
During his tenure as president of the American Postal Workers Union from 1980 until approximately 2001, Biller actively advanced labor history in New York City through his philanthropic support of numerous charitable organizations and educational institutions. The American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Records contain significant paper-based and photographic documentation, as well as artifactual evidence of Biller's career with the Postal Service, and his legacy.
Arrangement
The American Postal Workers Union: Moe Biller Files are arranged into four series, the first two of which are processed.
The series are as follows:
Missing Title
Subject Files, 1930-2001
Oral History Project Files: New York Metro Area Postal Union, 1962-1983
Photographs
Artifacts
Files within each series are ordered alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Postal Workers Union Photograph and Memorabilia Collection (inquire at reference desk)
New York Metro Area Postal Union Photographs (PHOTOS 011)
New York Metro Area Postal Union Records (WAG 103)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the American Postal Workers Union (APWU) president Moe Biller at the time of his retirement in the fall of 2001. The donation was confirmed by incoming president William Burrus. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2001.198 and 2001.199.
Correspondence.; Records (documents); Transcripts.; Strikes and lockouts |x Postal Workers.; Washington (D.C.); Postal Strike, U.S., 1970.; United States Postal Service |x Employees |x History.; New York (N.Y.).; Clippings (information artifacts); Postal service |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; New York Metro Area Postal Union; Goodman, Sidney; American Postal Workers Union; Salk, Charles; Schechter, Dana; Biller, Moe, 1915-2003; American Postal Workers Union; Biller, Moe, 1915-2003; Burrus, William
- Series I: Subject Files, 1930-2001
  Scope and Content Note
  Includes correspondence, reports, flyers and clippings documenting Moe Biller's years as president of the New York Metro Area Postal Union (APWU, Local 10). Especially well represented are materials reflecting health and safety hazards in the industry, and the union's energetic attempts to improve working conditions. A smaller amount of material (mostly convention records, daily schedules, expense records, and committee materials) relate to Biller's tenure as international president of the American Postal Workers Union. Also included are a range of records and printed ephemera documenting the Depression-era history of U.S. postal workers and their organizations; these were given to Moe Biller by various members of the APWU over the years.
  - American Federation of Labor: Di Bartolomeo Materials, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advertising Tracking Study, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Americans for Democratic Action: Award to Moe Biller, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - APWU: Birmingham, AL Local, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - APWU: History, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - APWU News, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - APWU: Rossdale Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - APWU vs. U.S. Postal Service, San Francisco Bulk Mail Center, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arbitration Procedure, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Arbitration Procedure and Cases, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining: Agreement, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining: Overtime Dispute (Article 8), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Barry, D. John, undated, 1966, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Benefits: General, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Biller, Anne, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Biller, Moe: Biographical, undated, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Biller, Moe: Compensation and Benefits, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Biller, Moe: Joke Newspapers, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bolger, William F., undated, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Bowing to Billerism and Other Matters": Fortune Magazine, Jun 1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Bulk Battle": News Flash, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Catholic Interracial Council of New York: Award to J. McMillan, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Capitol Building Access: APWU Officers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Civil Service: Pamphlets, 1955, 1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clerk Craft Conference, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clinton, William J., President: MB Support For, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings: Federal Times, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clippings: New York Daily News, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clippings: New York Post, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Clippings: New York Times, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Clippings: The Progressive, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Clippings: Washington DC Press, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Committee on Political Action, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Committees, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Concerned Postal Workers: Workers Action Movement, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, undated, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Contract Stations: Problems, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Convention, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Convention: Amnesty for Fired Postal Workers, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Convention: Las Vegas, Wedding Ceremony, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Convention: Location Complaint, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Convention: Resolutions, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1961-1986 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - DiBartolomeo, Mando: Collection of Material on Postal History, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Diary of Events, Nov 1980-Dec 1980 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Discrimination Complaint: N. Atkinson, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Drug Enforcement: In Post Office, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Elections: APWU, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Elections: APWU, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Elections: APWU, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Elections: APWU Vice-President, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Elections: Federal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Ellis Island: Awards Gala, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Expenses: Moe Biller, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Fair Labor Standards Act: Lawsuits, etc., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Federal Service: General, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Filbey, Francis S., 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal Crisis: NYC, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AFreeze March@: Clippings (from Max Eastman), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Scheme of Alabama, Arkansas, Kansas, Missouri (Donated to APWU by Robert D. Kessler), 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Glossary of Postal Terms, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Goodman, Sidney: Death, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Goodman, Sidney: General, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Goodman, Sidney: Retirement, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Goodman, Sidney: Testimony, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Goodwin, Leo: Schack Affair, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Grievances: General, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Handman, Ephraim (Frank): Charles Salk Account of, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Health and Safety: Accident Prevention, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Health and Safety: Asbestos, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Health and Safety: Morgan Mail Facility, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Health and Safety: Morgan Mail Facility, OSHA Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Health and Safety: Facility at New York Bulk and Foreign Mail Center, OSHA Report, etc., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Health and Safety: General, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Health and Safety: NY Bulk and Foreign Mail Center, OSHA Recommendations, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Health and Safety: NY Bulk and Foreign Mail Center, OSHA Survey, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Hiroshima Peace Memorial Museum, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Illinois Federation of Postal Clerks: Convention Proceedings, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Illinois Federation of Postal Clerks: DiBartolomeo Materials, 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Illinois Federation of Postal Clerks: Women's Auxilliary, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Iran: Robert Armao and the Shah, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Italian Americans in APWU, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Kay, Abe: Charles Salk Account of, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1965, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Komansky, Samuel: Life in the Postal Service, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Las Vegas Area Local, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Local Implementation: Arbitrator's Award, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Local Memorandum of Understanding: NY Bulk and Foreign Mail Center, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Locker Inspection: Protest, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Manhattan-Bronx Postal Union: Union Mail Clipping, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Methods Improvement Program, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Miami: Asbestos Protest, etc., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - National Association of Letter Carriers-APWU Arbitration Case, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - National Association of Letter Carriers: Branch 36, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - National Association of Substitute Post Office Employees: Leaflet, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - National Federation of Post Office Clerks: Mando DiBartolomeo Historical Materials, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - National Postal Clerks Union: Manhattan-Bronx Case, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - National Postal Union, 1960, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - New York Bulk and Foreign Mail Center, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - New York Federation of Post Office Clerks: Constitution and Bylaws, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New York Federation of Post Office Clerks: Contingency Fund, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - New York Metro Area Postal Union: Award to Moe Biller, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - New York Metro Area Postal Union: History, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - New York Metro Area Postal Union: Leaflets (with Charles Salk Comments), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - New York Metro Area Postal Union: ANews Flash@, 1970, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - New York Metro Area Postal Union: Women Stewards Meeting, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - OSHA: New Directions Grant Application, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Pay Rates, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Penn Terminal Employees: Hand-Drawn Card to Moe Biller, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Pension Adjustments, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Pepper, Claude: Banquet, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Postal Laws and Regulations, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Postal Press Association, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Postal Service, 1969-1986 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Postal Service: Arbitration Case (Costa, M.), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Postal Service: General, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Postal Service: History, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Postal Sub: National Union of Substitute Post Office Employees, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Postal Workers Defense Committee: San Francisco, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Postscript: The Voice of the NY Post Office, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Presidents' [sic] Conference, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "Remember Moe Biller?" Article, Army Magazine, Sep 1975 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Resolutions, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Retirement: Moe Biller (Photocopy of Album), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Revolutionary Union: Draft Program, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Riesel, Victor, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Safety Conditions: High-Volume Books, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Salk, Charles: General, 1972-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller (Calendar), 1981-1982, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller (Calendar), 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller (Calendar), 1991, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller (Calendar), 1995, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Schedule: Moe Biller (Calendar), 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scheme Committee (APWU and Postal Service): Meetings and Background Materials (I), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Scheme Committee (APWU and Postal Service): Meetings and Background Materials (II), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Scheme Committee (APWU and Postal Service): Meetings and Background Materials (III), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scotto Trial, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Selective Service Registration: Objection by Postal Clerks, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - South Shore Area Local 3844: "The Weird", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Strachan, John R.: Manhattan Postmaster, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Strike: Article on National Guard Role (Army Magazine), Sep 1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Strike: Articles, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Strike: Charles Salk File, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Strike: Charles Salk "The Eve of the Strike", Jul 1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Strike: Chronology of Events, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Strike: Threats, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Strike: Union Mail, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27a)
  - Strike: U.S. v. Branch 36, NALC, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Substitute Post Office Clerks Association: Newsletter, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Substitute Post Office Employees Association, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Supervisory Personnel (204B) Returning to Bargaining Unit: Grievances, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Taxes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Telecommunication Deregulation, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Union Democracy: Attendance Requirements, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Union Recognition: Biller Testimony, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Union Mail: Manhattan, Bronx Clerks, 1960, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - U.S. Labor Department Suit: Back Pay, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - U.S. v. APWU, et al.: Limitation of Hours, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wiretapping: Britain, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Working Conditions: Washington, DC, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Series II: Oral History Project Files, New York Metro Area Postal Union, 1962-1983
  The New York Metro Area Postal Union's Oral History Project Files consists of background files, transcripts and other documentation produced and collected in the course of an oral history project supervised by Dana Schechter in the late 1970s and carried out by retired postal workers. The audio tapes produced by this project make up oral history collection OH 3 at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives. The oral history project includes a lengthy interview with Moe Biller, covering his early life and his years as president of the New York Metro Area Postal Union.
  - Blacksin, Harry, 1962-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Transfer Agreement, Questionnaire, List of Interviewees, 1976-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Transcripts: Aronberg, Arnie (Notes), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Transcripts: Biller, Moe, Jul 1976-Aug 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Transcripts: Biller, Moe (Notebook), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Transcripts: Biller, Moe, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Transcripts: Biller, Moe on Strike Chronology, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Transcripts: Epstein, Max, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Transcripts: Excerpts, Building the Union, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Transcripts: Excerpts, Misc., undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Transcripts: Excerpts, Pivotal Events, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Transcripts: Excerpts, Working Conditions, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Transcripts: Goldberg, Bernard, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Transcripts: Group 1: Rosner, Salk, Ryland, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Transcripts: Group 2: Rosner, Salk, Ryland, Epstein, Rock, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Transcripts: Kamish, Harry, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Transcripts: Kaye, Abe, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Transcripts: Mandel, Sidney, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Transcripts: Resnick, Elsie, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Transcripts: Resnick, Robert, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Transcripts: Rosner, Milt, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Transcripts: Ryland, Arthur, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Transcripts: Salk, Charles, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Transcripts: Seligman, Philip, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Unprocessed, undated (Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9)
- Series IV: Artifacts
  - Awards/Plaques (Box 10, Box 11, Box Shared Tamiment 011, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit Panels (Box 12)
  - Louisville Slugger Baseball Bat (Box 13)